[Music]
Professor Dave and CH here a very
important thing to be able to do in
organic chemistry is to be able to
assign the formal charge of any atom in
a particular molecule atoms can be of
neutral charge or they can have a
positive or negative charge and
identifying atoms that have these
charges will help us predict what
molecule will do so let's make sure we
know how to do this the main thing to
understand is that an atom will be of
neutral charge when it is contributing a
number of electrons to a leis structure
that is equal to its veence for example
carbon has four veence electrons so when
it makes four bonds it contributes one
electron to each and is thus neutral
nitrogen has five veence electrons so
when it makes three bonds and has one
lone pair it is neutral If instead it
makes four bonds it contributes only
four electrons which is one less than
its veence so it has a formal positive
charge oxygen has six veence electrons
so when it makes two bonds and has two
lone pairs it is neutral but if it makes
only one Bond and has three loone pairs
it contributes seven electrons which is
one more than its veence so it will have
a formal negative charge this is the
easiest way to tell the formal charge of
any atom within a molecule here are the
most common situations we will be seeing
over and over again in organic chemistry
starting with carbon species here is a
carbon radical with three bonds and one
unpaired electron a carbo cation with
three bonds and an empty fourth
coordination site and a carban ion with
three bonds and one loone pair these are
neutral positively charged and
negatively charged respectively carbon
has four veence electrons but the
electrons being contributed to these
structures are four 3 and five
respectively so a carbon radical is
neutral just like a carbon that is
participating in four bonds a
carbocation has a formal positive charge
and a carban ion has a formal negative
charge then for nitrogen we have three
bonds and one loone pair four bonds and
no loone pairs or two bonds and two
loone pairs nitrogen has five veence
electrons and here we see contributions
of five 4 and six that means we have
neutral nitrogen
positively charged nitrogen and
negatively charged nitrogen moving on to
oxygen again we have two bonds and two
loone pairs three bonds and one loone
pair and then one Bond and three loone
pairs oxygen has six veence electrons
but these contribute six 5 and seven
respectively so we have neutral oxygen
positively charged oxygen and negatively
charged oxygen or an oxyanion which we
will see frequently then sulfur will
behave Just Like Oxygen since it also
has six veence electrons so by replacing
these oxygen atoms with sulfur atoms all
the same charges will apply and then
phosphorus is an analog of nitrogen and
we will sometimes see a phosphorus
cation when it is making four bonds to
other
atoms it is very important that this
ability of assigning formal charge to
any atom in a molecule becomes intuitive
because we need to know where the
charges are on a molecule to understand
how it reacts with other molecules
Professor Dave for che see you next
time